[Music]
everyone knows that pollution is bad
the w-h-o estimates the air pollution
alone kills about six and a half million
people a year that's 10% of all deaths
and more than AIDS malaria and
tuberculosis combined in recent years
however better more credible research
from economists and others has taught us
that pollution it's even worse than we
thought I'm gonna cover a few of the
most interesting studies in this video
infants born in places with a lot of
pollution they tend to be born with
worse health more premature births and
lower birth weight for example but
infants born in places with worse
pollution they also tend to be different
in other ways they're born to poorer
families so what's causing the health
problems
is it the pollution or is it the poverty
one way to tell would be to run an
experiment to randomly assign pregnant
women some too high pollution areas
others too low pollution areas and then
after some time to compare the health of
their infants probably not too many
women would volunteer for that
experiment the introduction of the
e-zpass in New Jersey in Pennsylvania
around the year 2000 however created an
ingenious natural experiment now some of
you might remember the old toll booths
where cars had to slow down give their
money to a toll booth worker get change
that meant long delays lots of
congestion and lots of pollution near
toll booths that all changed with the
introduction of electronic tolling EZ
Pass long lines of the toll booth were
eliminated as cars zipped through fast
lanes creating much less local pollution
The Economist's Jana curry and Reed
Walker they collected information about
the health of infants born near toll
booths
before and after the introduction of EZ
Pass infants born near toll booths there
the treatment group because these
infants were exposed to much more
pollution before EZ Pass
then after EZ Pass other factors however
they might be changing through time so
to control for these other factors Curry
and Walker found a group of infants who
were born more than two kilometers away
from the toll booth but less than ten
kilometers away and within three
kilometers of a major highway now these
infants they don't live near enough to
the toll booth to be affected by the
change in pollution but they do live
near enough to the toll booths and a
major highway to form a good control
group a group that is likely to have
similar dynamics to the treatment group
so this is called a
difference-in-difference design because
it compares the difference in infant
health of the treatment group before and
after EZ Pass to the difference in
infant health of the control group
before and after EZ Pass if the control
group has similar dynamics to the
treatment group this
difference-in-difference method will
produce a causal estimate of the impact
of air pollution on infant health using
this method Curry and Walker found that
the introduction of EZ Pass reduce low
birth weight babies by about eight and a
half percent and premature births by
about seven and a half percent the also
found that the effects were largest for
the infants born closest to the toll
booth a dose-response effect
these are big effects especially as
being born with low birth weight or
being born premature that can have
effects such as lower IQ and worse
health that lasts a lifetime pollution
of course doesn't just affect infants
three economists measured pollution at a
series of chess tournaments in Germany
they compared each player's moves
with the moves that the player should
have made according to the world's
greatest player of chess magnus carlsen
know the stockfish 9ai
and what they discovered is that the
human players they made more mistakes on
days with higher pollution and other
studies have found similar results call
center workers in China they're less
productive on high pollution days even
baseball umpires have been found to make
more errors calling balls and strikes
when pollution is high what we're
learning from a wide variety of studies
is that pollution reduces health IQ
productivity and employment in other
words pollution is an attack on human
capital and human capital is the most
important input to the economy and what
that means is that less pollution can
mean more GDP we may be on the wrong
side of the pollution laughs recur and
if less pollution can mean more GDP even
in a relatively low pollution society
like the United States then this is
probably doubly and trebly true in high
pollution societies like China and
especially India in one sense this news
is bad pollution is making us sick and
stupid in another sense the news is good
pollution is so bad that reducing it can
make us healthier and wealthier and we
have the technologies to reduce
pollution but using solar nuclear and
natural gas and now new research shows
that the benefits of reducing pollution
it could be much greater than we
previously imagined ready to keep
learning answering a few quick questions
will help you retain this material also
economists call pollution and
externality this video will help you
better understand externalities are you
a teacher
check out econ inbox calm which is a
free weekly email that brings more
real-world examples of externalities and
other econ concepts into your classroom